{"tossups": [{"question": "This organization\u2019s creation was built on a \u201crisk theory\u201d that its rival would allow it to become a superpower rather than risk a pitched battle. This organization was expanded under three Novelles, the first of which ordered the creation of four Nassau class ships. This force was expanded by Alfred von Tirpitz, which responded to the Great Britain\u2019s Dreadnought with an arms race prior to WWI. For ten points, name this naval force that was expanded greatly under Wilhelm II.", "answer": "Imperial<b> German navy</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cthe Navy\u201d or \u201cthe armed forces of Germany\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this event, George Clinton led a crowd that congregated at Murray\u2019s Wharf and escorted a man to 3 Cherry Street. A participant in this event was forced to walk to Franklin House after an overwhelming number of people in the street blocked his carriage. During this event, Robert Livingston exclaimed \u201clong live [its subject]!\u201d after administering the oath of office. For ten points, name this 1789 event in which America\u2019s first President was sworn in.", "answer": "George<b> Washington\u2019s first inauguration</b> (\u201dfirst\u201d not needed after \u201c1789\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One member of this family founded a firm called<em> Serp</em> that sold historic music recordings, including themes from Nazi marches; that member of this family controversially claimed that \u201cJewish organizations\u201dfinancially controlled Jacques Chirac. In 2017, a member of this family came second to the leader of the <em>En Marche!</em> party, Emmanuel Macron. The far-right National Front is led by a member of, for ten points, what French political family whose members include Jean-Marie and Marine?", "answer": "<b> Le Pen</b> family", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "After being disappointed to find out that Hawikuh was not in fact one of these places, an explorer wrote that its residents \u201cworship water\u201d because it \u201cmakes corn grow.\u201d A slave named Estevanico helped popularize the legend of these places, which he and Cabeza de Vaca allegedly heard about during the Narvaez Expedition. Quivira was found not to be one of these places by a man who led an expedition that marked the first European sighting of the Colorado River. Francisco Coronado searched for, for ten points, what series of cities that were alleged to contain vast quantities of gold?", "answer": "<b> Seven Cities of Cibola</b> (accept<b> Seven Cities of Gold</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Mandatory, secular, and free education were established in a set of laws named for one prime minister in this government, Jules Ferry. One crisis faced by this government failed to be resolved by L\u00b4eon Blum\u2019s Popular Front. This government was threatened by Georges Boulanger\u2019s revanchism for a province lost at this government\u2019s founding. Its first president, Adolphe Thiers, put down the Paris Commune. For ten points, name this French government that lasted from the Franco-Prussian War to the Second World War.", "answer": "French<b> Third Republic</b> (prompt on France, prompt on French Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Burmese saung is often thought to be the only surviving type of this instrument from Asia. A sonata for flute, violin, and this instrument was written by Claude Debussy, who wrote a glissando for it after the flute solo in<em> Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun</em>. High King Brian Boru supposedly owned one of these instruments depicted on the flag of the Province of Leinster. For ten points, name this plucked string instrument whose concert version has seven pedals and whose Celtic version is found on the Irish coat of arms.", "answer": "<b> harp</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man accused the East India Company of the destruction of \u201cmonuments of real kings\u201d in the Carnatic region and other abuses in his speech<em> The Nabob of Arcot\u2019s Debts</em>. This man\u2019s most famous work, a response to the sermon<em> A Discourse on the Love of Our Country</em> by Richard Price, claims that Jacques Necker was an \u201cAble financier\u201d and finds that the \u201cimprovements of the National Assembly are superficial.\u201d For ten points, name this conservative thinker who wrote<em> Reflections on the Revolution in</em> <em>France</em>.", "answer": "Edmund<b> Burke</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At this event, a judge was told \u201cHe\u2019s strong every way!\u201d when he asked whether Abraham Lincoln could fight. The organizers of this event vowed to prohibit the \u201ctwin relics of barbarism: polygamy and slavery.\u201d This event was held at the Musical Fund Hall in Philadelphia, whose home state offered raucous support for Supreme Court Justice John McLean. A future ambassador to France, William Dayton, was nominated for Vice President at, for ten points, what convention that nominated John C. Fremont as the first presidential candidate for the Republican Party?", "answer": "<b> 1856 R</b>epublican<b> N</b>ational<b> C</b>onvention", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Peter Chartier tried to limit the sale of rum to these people, a group of whom were led by John Linney into Mexico and later compensated by Mirabeau Lamar. One of these people named Blackfish led the Siege of Boonesborough and captured Daniel Boone. A war led by one of these people was motivated by the Treaty of Fort Wayne. Many tribes joined a war led by a member of this Native American group that ended at the Battle of Tippecanoe. For ten points, name this Algonquian group whose leaders included\u201cthe Prophet\u201d Tenskwatawa and Tecumseh.", "answer": "<b> Shawnee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this event took place, Tecumseh was visiting allies in Cape Girardeau, roughly 50 miles from its center.", "answer": "<b> New Madrid Earthquake</b> (prompt on \u201cearthquake\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man passed the first set of sweeping welfare measures in British history.", "answer": "Herbert Henry \u201cH.H.\u201d<b> Asquith</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This author created Baldassare, a character who kills his own adoptive son because he had participated in political intrigue during the reign of Savonarola. Shortly before the passage of the Second Reform Act, this author wrote a novel in which Harold Transome loses an election in 1832 while running as a\u201cRadical.\u201d The power-hungry Tito Mamale marries the title character of this author\u2019s novel<em> Romola</em>. For ten points, name this author of<em> Felix Holt</em> who again tackled the theme of political reform through the character of Dorothea Brooke\u2019s uncle in her novel<em> Middlemarch</em>.", "answer": "George<b> Eliot</b> (or Mary Anne<b> Evans</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "The \u201cPrivate Blank Check\u201d system was used in this event. Lanny Davis called indictments for this event as \u201cbizarre\u201d due to its close proximity to an election. Lawrence Walsh was made independent counsel to investigate this event, which involved Manucher Ghorbanifar and other dealers, as well as the release of Reverend Benjamin Weir from Lebanon. This event was blamed on the President\u2019s \u201clax managerial style,\u201d according to a commission led by former Texas Senator John Tower. Caspar Weinberger and John Poindexter were investigated in, for ten points, what 1980s affair that led to Oliver North\u2019s arrest after destroying evidence of arms deals?", "answer": "<b> Iran-Contra</b> Affair (or<b> Contragate</b> or<b> Irangate</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "When this man sent a messenger to his father to ask advice, the father silently lopped the heads off of the tall poppies with a stick; the confused messenger relayed the story, after which this man executed the leaders of Gabii. The road on which this man\u2019s predecessor was assassinated became known as the Street of Crime. This man\u2019s son-in-law, Octavius Mamilius, was killed fighting alongside this man at the Battle of Lake Regillus. This man once attempted to ally with a leader of Clusium named Lars Porsena in an attempted march on Rome. This successor of Servius Tullius was overthrown after the rape of Lucretia. For ten points, name this final king of Rome.", "answer": "Lucius<b> Tarquinius Superbus</b> (accept<b> Tarquin the Proud</b>; prompt on Tarquin)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A telegram sent to John Abbott during this event ended \u201cdo not fail me; answer today.\u201d Thomas McGreevy was sentenced to a year in jail for his role in this event, which prompted Hector Langevin to resign from politics. This scandal was exposed partly because Hugh Allan used American money to fund Conservative politicians. The secret ballot was introduced in response to, for ten points, what 19th century political scandal that temporarily toppled Canadian Prime Minister John Macdonald after revelations of railroad-related bribery?", "answer": "<b> Pacific</b> Scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Forces under this man killed King Poppo at the Battle of Boarn. In a victory for this man, retreating soldiers left their tents behind after his scouts discovered their loot from</b> <b>Bordeaux. This man defeated Ragenfred and (+)</b> <b>Childeric II at the Battle of Vincy,</b> <b>essentially removing them from a 715 civil war. This man served in both Neustria and Austrasia as (*)</b> Mayor of the Palace until his 741 death. Abdul Rahman Al Ghafiqi was defeated by this man in a battle that halted the Muslim conquest of Europe. For ten points, name this victor at Tours, a Frankish King known as \u201cthe Hammer.\u201d", "answer": "Charles<b> Martel</b> (accept<b> Charles the Hammer</b> before mentioned, and prompt on it afterward; prompt on Charles; accept \u201cKarl\u201d in place of Charles)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Prior to this battle an army convened at Tjaru before marching over the ridge of Mount Carmel. This battle was fought partly for control of a trade route that was once called \u201cthe Way of the Philistines.\u201d The first recorded use of the (+) composite bow was at this battle, which is partly recorded in temple inscriptions at Karnak. The King of Kadesh commanded Canaanite forces at this battle, which was a victory for a member of the (*) </b> 18th Dynasty. For ten points, name this 15th century BC victory for Thutmose III of Egypt.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Megiddo</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The units of this text include Gond, Nut-Narayan, Asa, and Manjh. Historians like Balh, Nalh, and Jalap contributed to this text. After the composition of this text, the musician</b> <b>Bhai Mardana traveled with its author, who became a bed of (+)</b> <b>flowers after he died. A</b> <b>verse from this text speaks of merchants whose \u201cprofits are preordained.\u201d This text, which was written after a religious figure was (*) </b> submerged in a river for three days, was written in the Gurmukhi Script. Gobind Singh declared that the final leader of his religion was, for ten points, what work written by Guru Nanak, the holy book of Sikhism?", "answer": "<b> Adi Granth</b> (accept Sri Guru<b> Granth</b> Sahib)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>An early recorded name for this location translates as \u201cSeven Lines of Abnal.\u201d D\u00b4esir\u00b4e Charnay provided a modern survey of this site, which was conquered by Hunac Ceel. A road called a</b><em><b> sacbe</b></em><b> connects this site to a location at which (+) Chaac was worshiped; that sinkhole, north of this city, is the Sacred Cenote [sen-OH-teh]. Thirteen ballcourts can be found at this site, where the deity (*) </b> Kukulcan is the dedicatee of a large step pyramid. For ten points, name this site in the Yucatan that was the home of an ancient Mayan city.", "answer": "<b> Chichen Itza</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Catherine Fulton organized a protest during this country\u2019s 1893 election after Walter Carncross purposefully doomed a suffrage amendment. The first female mayor in the British</b> <b>Empire, Elizabeth Yates, served in this country\u2019s city of (+)</b> <b>Onehunga. Two politicians</b> <b>in this country changed their vote on suffrage in protest of Richard Seddon\u2019s underhanded tactics. (*)</b> Kate Sheppard fought for women\u2019s suffrage in this country and replaced Elizabeth II on the 10-dollar note. For ten points, name this country where an 1893 electoral act gave Maori women the right to vote.", "answer": "<b> New Zealand</b>  (1) <b>An equestrian statue of this man wearing bandoliers commemorates his victory</b> <b>at Zacatecas. This man was photographed wearing a dark jacket and sitting in the presidential chair with one of his allies who has taken off his hat. This man allied</b> <b>his own forces from (+)</b> <b>Chihuahua with a Liberation Army of the South led by a</b> <b>man from Morelos. After this man lost the Battle of Celaya, his (*)</b> raid on the town of Columbus, New Mexico prompted a punitive expedition in 1916. For ten points, name this Mexican bandit and revolutionary who sided with Emiliano Zapata and was chased by Black Jack Pershing. ANSWER: Francisco \u201cPancho\u201d<b> Villa</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}